Today's דף daf is ע"ג. Ayin Gimmel. We begin a new פרק,
perek, המוכר את הספינה. Hamocher Es Hasfina. This is going to sort
of same basic issue as the previous פרק. perek. When you sell
something, what's included? Except moving away from land. Landed property it speaks
about chattel. Starts with a boat, which is still a very big
piece of מטלטלין, metaltelin, and the גמרא Gemara
and then we'll move on. But as many people might know, we
will see the next few days actually are going to be really
focused, not focused, are going to be אגדתא, aggadata, it's a major
segment, section of אגדתא aggadata here in the גמרא Gemara as we
will see momentarily. So let's take a look. המוכר את הספינה מכר
את התורן, Hamocher es hasfina machar es hatoran, if you sell a
boat, included in the boat is the mast,
and את הנס, es hanes, and the sails. What? The sails.
The sails. ואת העוגין, ve'es ha'ugin, the anchors.
We're going to say that in the גמרא. Gemara. ואת כל המנהיגין
אותה, ve'es kol hamahiginosah, all those things that cause that lead it,
like literally they lead it but basically make it move, the oars.
Exactly. אבל לא מכר לא את העבדים, aval lo machar lo es
ha'avadim, you do not sell the slaves that, right, the crew, exactly,
but they would be owned. Okay. They also make it move, but
you know, but they are people, so slaves are separate. ולא את
המרצופין, velo es hamartzufim, not the bags that you would keep the
you know the wares in, the what's it called the what would
be the name for that? The chests? No. Yeah, yeah, but no
I mean no I know it's a sack, no, I'm looking for
the word. Whatever. Sacks? No, the stuff that you're transporting. Cargo. Cargo.
Thank you. Okay.
מרצופין martzufim mean what?
They are sacks. What?
Like שקים? sakim?
No, I don't know, different word. ולא את האנטיקי, velo es ha'antiki,
אנטיקי antiki is the cargo. ובזמן שאמר לו היא וכל מה שבתוכה,
ubizman she'amar lo hi vechol mah shebetochah, when you say it and
all that's in it, so הרי כולן מכורין, harei kulan mechorin, it's
all sold. Including? Yeah, the slaves? Sure.
But they're not like in it, they like move.
Yeah, but I that's true, it doesn't necessarily mean I guess we're
not taking it totally literally. I mean it means that they are
sort of part of it. It's a good point though because if
you think back about the whole issue about the land, right? When
you take כל מה שבתוכה kol mah shebetochah you do not include
the slaves, is that right? I'm trying to remember about the bathhouse.
Right, I think that was explicit about or
no no no, it says like this, המוכר את העיר מכר בתים
בורות שיחין ומערות, hamocher es ha'ir machar batim boros shichin umearos, אבל
לא מטלטלין ובזמן שאמר היא וכל מה שבתוכה אפילו היה בהמה ועבדים
הרי כולן מכורין. aval lo metaltelin uvizman she'amar hi vechol mah shebetochah
afilu hayah behemah va'avadim harei kulan mechorin. So it's ס"ח, Samech Ches,
it's the same thing that if slaves are part of and there
it was a part of a city of a town where they
weren't necessarily a necessary part of the, if you excuse for a
second, the equipment. Right here you need the slaves as part of
the, you know, as part of the rowers, as part of the
crew in order to I mean you don't need them to be
slaves but you need people in order to make the thing function.
Yeah, that was the חידוש chiddush of the משנה. Mishnah. All right,
so now let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. תורן Toran
is איסקריא, iskarya, which is a mast. If you look at the
רשב"ם, Rashbam, mast.
שפורסין עליו את הוילון בראש הספינה. sheporsin alav es havilon be'rosh hasfina.
וכן הוא אומר ארז מלבנון לקחו לעשות תורן עליך. vechein hu omer
erez milevanon lakachu la'asos toran alayich. So they took the the cedars
from the Lebanon to make a mast on you. This is a
and therefore clearly a cedar is a very tall tree, so by
context it's clear we're talking about a mast. Okay. נס Nes is
אדרא adra is the is the sail. וכן הוא אומר שש ברקמה
ממצרים היה מפרשך להיות לך לנס, vechein hu omer sheish berikmah mimitzrayim
hayah mafriseich lihyos lach lenes, the like embroidered linen from Egypt was
the thing that was spread over you,
to be for you for a sail. So again we're obviously talking
about something woven that is spread, so by context we're talking about
the sail.
And you see that in like a נס nes as in a
miracle.
Yeah, well I mean the רמב"ן Ramban discusses that on אבל הוא
כי נסה את
אברהם aval hu ki nisa es Avraham so נס nes whether the
purpose of the נסיון nisayon is to is to demonstrate, you know,
Avraham's greatness and to raise up like you raise up a flag,
right, נס nes also is a miracle to also to call attention
to something. So yes, there are some possible associations there.
How do you get from נס nes to sail?
No, well a flag is something high that's raised up that you
see that flaps in the wind and so on. What?
Is that what was used in the מדבר midbar where שבט shevet
had?
איש על דגלו, ish al diglo, I mean there it uses the
phrase דגל, degel, but yeah. Of course נס nes is the ensign,
which is a
flag.
Ensign. Oh, but an ensign is that's just the flag that basically
as it's literally the flag that like says like this is the
name this is the boat, the identity of the boat. Right. Not
this sounds like it's something I mean spread over the it's the
main sail is the way it sounds I thought from context certainly
from the רשב"ם. Rashbam.
I don't know. Anyway. Okay.
All right. עוגין, Ugin, what are the עוגין? ugin? תני רבי חייא.
tani Rabbi Chiya. אלו אוגנין, Eilu Oginin, from
so now, which clearly means from the word אוגן ogen or עגונה
aguna we'll see in a minute, which is an anchor. Okay, שלה.
shelah. וכן הוא אומר עליהן תסברנה עד אשר יגדלו, V'chein hu omer
aleihen tisabeirna ad asher yigdalu, now
shifting from Yechezkel to Rut, הלהן תעגנה, Halehen te'ageina,
right, will you be, will you be sort of long after them,
you know, even were I to have children yet to bear, would
you long after them until they would grow up, will you be
anchor yourself to them? מפקיע יו"ד, Mipkia Yud, ah yes, so it
is the same source as עגונה, Aguna, a woman who is anchored.
Okay. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says, if you look at the רשב"ם,
Rashbam, אוגנין, Oginin, the רשב"ם Rashbam says anchors של ברזל. shel barzel.
I just want to point out the interesting that it's the same
word ומשליכין במים להעמיד הספינה במקום אחד. Umashlichin bamayim l'ha'amid hasafina b'makom
echad. Okay.
So now מנהיגין, Manhigin, what are the מנהיגין? Manhigin? אמר רבי אבא,
Amar Rabbi Abba, אלו המשוטין שלה, Eilu hameshotin shelah,
the things that you use to make it sail, move, so the
oars. וכן הוא אומר, V'chein hu omer, אלונים מבשן עשו משוטיך. Alonim
mibashan asu moshotaich. So
from the אלון, alon, what type of a tree is an אלון?
alon? An oak? Okay, oaks from from the Bashan they used for
your oars, again the same context of some tall wood thing, so
it's the oars. ואיבעית אימא מהכא, V'iba'it eima meihacha, וירדו מאניותיהם כל
תופשי משוט. Vayerdu me'oniyoteihem kol tofshei mashot.
So they went down, came down from their boats, all that hold
onto the משוט, mashot, so again from context we're talking about those
that hold and row the boat with the oars. תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, המוכר את הספינה מכר את האיסקלא, Hamocher et hasafina machar et
ha'iskala,
if you sell you also sell, if you sell a boat, also
what's not mentioned in the Mishnah is you also sell the איסקלא,
iskala, which the רשב"ם Rashbam says means the ramp.
What's the gangplank? Right, thank you.
Okay. ואת
בור המים, V'et bor hamayim,
and the big cistern of water, of sweet water that you would
have on the boat obviously, fresh water שבתוכה. shebeitocha. רבי נתן אומר,
Rabbi Natan omer,
המוכר את הספינה. Hamocher et hasafina.
Does it mean the water or the or like just the barrel
you put the water in?
No, oh that's an interesting point. You're right, it does say the
בור המים. bor hamayim. I was assuming it meant with the water
but maybe not, you're right, because you know, fill it up with
your own darn water. That's a good point. Okay, that's a good
point.
Okay, because bottom line is if you think about it and oh,
you know, I should pause for a moment here and talk about
something about what makes this distinct. When you're selling land, the basic
assumption was where you were not selling cattle,
movables, even movables that were like a necessary part of, you know,
of tending to the land. There were a few exceptions maybe about
some of the trellises about the vineyard, but basically the point was
was that things that were
movable, מטלטלין, metaltelin, were not sold with land. Here you're the whole
boat although it's huge could be used is itself a מטלטלין metaltelin
and so you do actually sell some all the list of things
you sell with it, you know, obviously are also מטלטלין metaltelin and
but things that are like not nailed down, right, things that are
necessary part of it but are not physically attached, so there's definitely
a חידוש chiddush in there. Fundamentally what you don't sell are the,
you know, are slaves, right, so they're obviously they have their own
autonomy I mean not autonomy whatever under their own control but you
know they are מטלטלי דניידי, metalteli d'naydi, they move on their own
volition. The cargo which is obviously a variable thing, you know, it's
not a regular part of the boat and the sacks which are
seen like more associated with the cargo less directly associated with the
boat. Okay, but the basic point is that you to sell things
that are not nailed down that are not physically attached that are
part of it. The other important thing that the רשב"ם Rashbam points
out is the רשב"ם Rashbam says that the reason this פרק perek
and this comes after the previous משנה mishna which was about הקדש,
hekdesh, can't forget that the previous משנה mishna was about הקדש, hekdesh,
after that challenging סוגיא sugya yesterday, is that he says that you
know we said that when you give a gift or you're מקדיש
makdish something then even things that are not normally included are included.
And the רשב"ם Rashbam says the reason to situate this פרק perek
after that was to tell you that that's true when you're dealing
with land. So when you're dealing with land, you know, things are
more seen as I don't know like, you know, somehow the land
itself is so important it's easier to see things as appendages to
the land so when you're giving a gift we could say oh
you gave a gift of the land it included all the stuff
in the land. But if you gave a gift of a boat
for example you would say that wouldn't include the cargo. So it's
a little ironic, you know, on the one hand because we're dealing
with מטלטלין metaltelin that means that you can sell other מטלטלין metaltelin
with this מטלטלין. metaltelin. When you sell land you don't usually include
stuff that's not physically attached and here when you sell a boat
and other types of מטלטלין metaltelin you can sometimes sell stuff that's
not physically attached. So on the one hand it's like easier to
bundle stuff together they're seen as more like one package because it's
all מטלטלין metaltelin and on the other hand the stuff that you
don't sell רשב"ם Rashbam says that would be considered excluded even like
if you say כל מה שבתוכה kol mah shebeitocha it's included. Let's
read the רשב"ם, Rashbam, okay, together so you can see.
He says like this, he says וכל הני, vechol hani, it is
three lines, the one, one, two, three lines down in the wide
lines or in the narrow lines after the wide lines at the
top. He says וכל הני נמי ליתנהו בכלל הקדש, vechol hani nami
letneihu bechlal hekdesh, שאם הקדיש את הספינה, she'im hikdish et hasfinah, לא
הקדיש את אלו, lo hikdish et elu, כדקתני להו בפרקין דלעיל. kedcatnei
lehu befirkin deleil. Okay, so the reason it comes after the discussion
of הקדש hekdesh was to say that הקדש hekdesh which is everything
in it would include the cargo, whereas if you're מקדיש makdish it,
it wouldn't. Or if you're מקדיש makdish it or everything in it.
No, well, he said everything in it would include but if you
just said the boat. Okay, but as opposed to when you're מקדיש
makdish land, for example, it includes the trees and the well and
you know and even the you know and even the what do
you call it the sycamore or whatever. והיינו טעמא vehaynu ta'ama דכל
הני דחשיבנא בפרקין דלעיל, dechol hani dechashivna befirkin deleil, בית המרחץ, beit
hamerchatz, בית הבד, beit habad, העיר, ha'ir, והשדה, vehasadeh, כולהו מקרקעי
נינהו. culhu mekarkei ninhu. They're all land. וכל הני דחשיב לא מכרן,
vechol hani dechashiv lo machran, all the things that you normally are
not included, נקנין קצת אגב ארעא לגבי הקדש ומתנה niknin ktzat agav
ar'a legabei hekdesh umatanah וחלוקת אגב. vechalucat agav. So because it's land
and land is so sort of you know the most basic thing,
the more important and fundamental thing as as opposed to chattel, so
therefore we'll say when you're actually being מקדיש makdish land or giving
it as a gift, other stuff gets more packaged together. וכל הני
דהאי פירקא מטלטלין נינהו. vechol hani dehai pirka metaltelin ninhu. This chapter's
all dealing with stuff that's chattel. לא שנא מכר ולא שנא מתנה
והקדש, lo shena mecher velo shena matanah vehekdesh, כולהון שוין בהני דלא
מכר. culhon shavin behani delo machar. Where it doesn't matter whether sale
or gift or הקדש, hekdesh, since it's not like a something fundamental
and something secondary, right? Land is fundamental, מטלטלין metaltelin is secondary, this
is all מטלטלין. metaltelin. So we say if there are things that
are excluded, they're more fully excluded. וכשם שלא מכר כך לא הקדיש
ולא נתן. veche-shem shelo machar kach lo hikdish velo natan. It goes
the other way around. So that's I guess it's a little ironic
because if they're not so fundamentally excluded because if you say וכל
מה שבתוכה vechol ma shebetochah you get it, right? So it's still
a little fuzzy, right? So yeah, it's very hard to know what
the principles here are. On the one hand because it's מטלטלין, metaltelin,
you're more ready to say other מטלטלין metaltelin are included in the
initial package, right? So you have all these things: the sail, the
mast, the oars, all that type of stuff. By land, fundamentally the
מטלטלין metaltelin are not included in the package. And now we're saying
say the flip when it comes to the question about a הקדש
hekdesh or מתנה. matanah. If you're מקדיש makdish or give you know
as a מתנה matanah a piece of land, then you get automatically
everything, but not necessarily when it comes to stuff. I really can't
understand all of the logic. All right, but it is worth noting
you know before we start getting into this mode of just saying
A, B, C, and D are included, E, F, G, and H
are excluded, and if you say כל מה שבתוכה kol ma shebetochah
you get those also. Okay, that's going to be the basic structure.
So it's worth thinking though about the differences to the previous פרק.
perek. The one and so again just to repeat, one obvious difference
here is is that you sell movable things together with it even
though they're not physically attached, and that was basically not the rule
when you sold land, things that were movable and not attached were
not sold with it. And the רשב"ם Rashbam introduces a reverse difference
in terms of the question of a gift or הקדש, hekdesh, that
more stuff goes with it with land than opposed than it would
go with it with stuff. Okay, let's get back to the גמרא.
Gemara. גמרא Gemara says like this. תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So he
says המוכר את הספינה מכר את האהרי hamocher et hasfinah machar et
ha'ahari and the cistern ובור המים שבתוכה. uvor hamayim shebetochah. רבי נתן
אומר Rabbi Natan omer המוכר את הספינה מכר את הביצי.
hamocher et hasfinah machar
et habetzi. ואת הביצי. ve'et habetzi. You also sell the ביצי,
betzi, which is basically the little boat, there's got to be a
name for it, that gets dragged along with the ship, the dinghy,
and that gets dragged along with the ship that's made for like
you know for
transport right from the boat to the mainland, exactly. Because you can't
dock the main big ship on the land. סומכוס אומר Sumchus omer
המוכר את הספינה מכר את הדוגית. hamocher et hasfinah machar et hadugit.
So what's this דוגית? dugit? So אמר רבא amar Rava ביצי היינו
דוגית. betzi haynu dugit.
They're the same thing. So then why do we call it this
different? So listen to the sort of geographical awareness of the גמרא.
Gemara. So רבי נתן בבלאה הוה Rabbi Natan bava'ah hava קרי לה
בוצי. kari lah butzi. Rabbi Natan was from בבל, Bavel, so he
called it a בוצי, butzi, which is the term for it in
בבל. Bavel. כדאמרי אינשי ked'amrei inshi בוציאצא דמישן. butzi'atza demayshan.
Those little boats of מישן, Mayshan, which was a body of water.
So that's we know that that's an Aramaic expression. So the word
בוצי butzi is an Aramaic word. Like from like mud, ביצה.
bitza. Oh that's interesting.
Oh okay, that's nice. That's nice, okay. So okay, so מישן Mayshan
was a like was like a river. And סומכוס דבר ארץ ישראל.
Sumchus devar Eretz Yisrael. So Sumchus who comes from ישראל, Yisrael, land
of ישראל, Yisrael, קרי ליה דוגית. kari leih dugit. כדכתיב kedichtiv אחריתכן
בסירות דוגה. acharitchen besirot dugah. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says it basically
means like a fishing boat. And סיר sir is like a pot.
So the pot is something that floats like a little fishing boat.
Okay, and therefore that's a fishing pot? Well, that's it too. Okay,
that's okay. Okay,
that is the end of the defining of the terms of the
משנה Mishnah and now we move into a major section of אגדתא.
Aggadata. So you've heard about like a fish, what's it called, a
fish store? Not fish store. What is that term about? Yeah, fish
story. So anyway like tall tales. Okay, here we go. Okay. So
talking about fishing boats and okay. אמר רבה אמר רבה, Amar Rabbah
Amar Rabbah, said Rabbah, אשתעו לי נחותי ימא, ishtau li nechutei yama,
those who go down to the to the ocean to the sea
have told me the following stories about their about what they've seen
and their travels.
So האי גלא דמטבע לספינה hai gala d'mitba l'sefinah when a wave
comes to to drown a boat, you know, to to submerge a
boat, מתחזי כי ציציתא דנורא, mitchazi ki tzitzita denura, you see like
a fringe of like white fire.
At the top. White caps.
Yes, the foam at the top of a of a wave. Okay.
So ומחינן ליה באלוותא u'machinan lei b'alveta so so far that works,
ומחינן ליה באלוותא u'machinan lei b'alveta and now when you smite the
wave with like rod דחקיק עליה d'chakik aleih that
that carves into the rod are the following words: אהיה אשר אהיה,
Ehyeh Asher Ehyeh, יה השם צבאות, Yah Hashem Tzevaot, אמן אמן סלה,
Amen Amen Selah,
so a couple names of God there. Okay, so if you have
those rods these rods that have it carved into it and you
hit this huge wave that's about to drown the boat, ונייח v'nayach
then the wave will settle and then it won't drown the boat.
So this is what you have to do.
He should have done that in Jonah. Yeah I know, different story.
That's all they know.
Okay. I really don't now I really don't know what to make
of it. I mean obviously Rabbah's saying this is what I heard,
you know, people came back, you know, like
Gulliver's travels, you know, the base after I mean whatever, there's a
whole history of travelogues of people that go and they come back
and they write these stories about the amazing things that they've seen
obviously was highly highly exaggerated. And you know when you go to
the ocean like you know people have always like you know you
get caught in these storms and it's very you know people have
the long history of coming back and having you know believe you
know not even necessarily intentionally making it up like believe you've seen
these amazing things when you are out there. So he's reporting it,
not necessarily validating its truthfulness but he's reporting it. What's the purpose
of reporting it is an interesting question. I will say that the
stories here are going to get pretty fantastical.
And this led what these גמרות Gemarot was an interesting source of
the discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim about do we have to treat
אגדתא Aggadata literally because of all the אגדתות Aggadot that are hardest
to believe are literal are like the ones that we're going to
be seeing in this גמרא. Gemara. And led obviously many many ראשונים
Rishonim to say like some type like you should never take them
literal, like רמב"ם. Rambam. רמב"ם Rambam was a very had a very
he says this in the beginning of his פירוש המשניות Perush Hamishnayot
and whatever and in the and in חלק Chelek and he says
there are three types of people. He says there are those that
believe that the אגדתא Aggadata of חז"ל Chazal are literal and they
believe them. Those are the fools. Then there are the people that
think that the אגדתות Aggadot of חז"ל Chazal were meant literally and
that the and they think חז"ל Chazal were were stupid that they
could believe such stuff. Those are the רשעים. reshaim. And
then there are those that know that חז"ל Chazal only meant them
as metaphors. Alright and those are the smart people. Okay so anyway
so that's like the רמב"ם. Rambam.
What? But he's only two of them, right? You you you son.
You made maybe. Anyway so that's the רמב"ם. Rambam.
Others, you know others others like רשב"א, Rashba, others you know I'll
get back also to the מאירי. Meiri. In תורת הבית Torat Habayit
he basically says like no a general orientation should be to assume
that they're true, but sometimes it's like you know you can't believe
that they're true. You know so these גמרות Gemarot were like גמרות
Gemarot that were like pretty much good consensus that these were not
meant literally. Then the question of course becomes well then what's the
point of them? You know so the מהרש"א, Maharsha, the מהרש"א Maharsha
for example says that some of these issues about waves and drowning
and so on and the God's name that the waves are like
you know like the the classic metaphor, right, which is all of
the waves have come over my head you know the sense of
what? Right exactly עלי עברו, alai avaru, but that's meant literally and
metaphorically, right, the sense of like having
troubles and travails.
Exactly. So that the waves here according to the מהרש"א Maharsha are
the non-Jewish nations that have brought you know suffering to the Jews
and you know they've survived because of God's name and God's protection.
And so sort of that's his basic orientation to reading to reading
these. Yeah.
רמב"ן's Ramban son wrote an extensive treatment of how to do אגדתא
Aggadata and it's at the front of the עין יעקב. Ein Yaakov.
Yeah yeah so הרא"ה.
HaRa'ah. הרא"ה HaRa'ah who was a who treated אגדתות Aggadot more literally
most of the time wrote a פירוש אגדות Perush Aggadot you know
so so yeah.
It just occurred to me that הגר"א HaGra interprets the wave here
as היצר הרע. hayetzer hara.
Oh
that's interesting. Oh more internal battle than external ones. Oh that's nice.
The journey we take through life and the problems we confront. Ah
ah.
All of them really sync up with the יצר הרע. yetzer hara.
Oh that's nice. So it's the same idea it's like this something
that's out there to destroy us or but and the strength we
need but we're seeing it as an internal conflict than an external
one.
white on top is that you know the יצר הרע yetzer hara
comes and makes things look white and pure.
Oh, I see. That's nice. Right, then you have to sort of
get into the details here. Okay, so אמר רבה Amar Rabba said
Rabba: אישתעו לי נחותי ימא, ishto l'neichusei yama, those who go down
to the sea have told me, בין גלא לגלא bein gala l'gala
תלת מאה פרסי, tlas mei'a parsei, between one wave and the next
that you're having these waves crashing against you, there could be 300
פרסי. parsen. Now a פרסה parsa is four מיל, mil, a מיל
mil is a kilometer. Okay, so roughly 960 meters. So anyway, so
400, how much did we say? 300 פרסי? parsen? So that would
be 1200 kilometers. You can do the math. What is that? Like
about a kilometer is what? How much of a mile? Six-tenths of
a mile? So it's like 700 miles. Okay. So anyway, between the
wave and a wave is 300 פרסי, parsei, that's 700 miles. ורומיא
דגלא v'rumyei d'gala תלת מאה פרסה, tlas mei'a parsa, the height of
an individual wave is 300 פרסי, parsei, so what did we just
say, 400 miles or something? Anyway.
Right, so what we... what that means is in terms of suffering
then...
I understand. Let's first read it then we can do the analysis.
Anyway, I actually looked up last night, apparently the highest recorded wave
was like 1300, 1400 feet, which is like less, which is like,
you understand, half of a mile. A פרסה's parsa four mile, a
מיל mil is like 3000 feet, so it's like okay, but anyway
so this is a major... what?
...almost seems that way.
Exactly, well that's the point. You're in the ocean and these waves
they seem completely enormous, right? All right. Anyway, any time 300 is
usually a clue that we're talking about an exaggeration. It's like nowadays
you'd say there would be a million there was a million people
there, right? But a million miles high. So okay, 300 is clearly
a number of exaggeration. Okay, so 300 פרסי. parsei. זימנא חדא הוה
אזלינן באורחא, zimna chada hava azinan b'orchas,
once we were going on the way, except the way means here
on a sea journey, okay, not not a not a land route.
So I mean these are the... these are the... stay... stay... sailors.
They're... look... look with them. Right right, they said this. They they
reported this. Okay.
ודלינן גלא עד דחזינן בי מרבעתא דכוכבא, v'dalinan gala ad d'chazinan beei
marbeisa d'kochava, when a wave lifted us up until we came to
the resting place of a star, lifted us up to the high
heavens, okay, זוטא, zuta, a small star, והוה ליה כמבזר ארבעין גריווי
ברזל דחרדלא. v'hava lei k'mivzar arbayin grivyei barzal d'chardala. And now, so
the רשב"ם Rashbam says it means that the sort of space that
it was, the star was situated in, was like the space of
40 גריווי grivyei which are like אמות amos of of like of
a mustard seeds. Okay, I don't know why you'd use the measure
of mustard seeds, because the amount of land it takes to plant
that amount of mustard seeds or whatever, I don't expect to get
the the what do you call it, the exact... or the you
know the descriptor of the area. But anyway, it was situated in
this very, very large
space, okay. ואי דלינן טפי, v'ee dalinan tfei, had it lifted us
up higher, הוינא מיקלינן מהבליה, havina miklyinan mei'hevlei,
we would have been burnt from the heat of the star.
It's an interesting thought, back then they thought stars are heat I
guess.
Yeah, big red... Yeah, good point that they realized they were not
just light but also heat. Okay. ורמי ליה גלא קלא לחבריה, v'rami
lei gala kala l'chaverei, and this wave had gotten so high that
one wave was sort of like casting out a voice to the
other wave, and it was now it was actually speaking, it wasn't
just a sound. And it said the following:
חברתאי שבקת מידי בעלמא דלא שטפתיה, chavartai shavakt midi b'alma d'lo shatfetei,
have you let, my friend, have you left anything in the world
that you have not drowned? Because it thought that if the wave
was so high it must have submerged the entire world.
But so if you've left anything looks like it's time to destroy
the world, and maybe we'll resort to תהו ובהו, tohu vavohu, you're
so high so if there's anything left that you have not yet
submerged, אימא לן וניבדיה, emei lian v'navdei, let me know, I'll come
and I'll submerge it. Something from... Not exactly. אמר לה חברתה, amar
lah ha'acharei, the first wave said back, פוק חזי גבורתיה דמרך, pook
chazi gvurtei d'marach, so go look at the strength of your master,
of God.
Okay, מלא חוטא חלא ולא עברי, mlo chusa chala v'lo avri, you
know that there's a line of sand, just like a hair's breadth
what? A line of sand? A line in the sand. A hair's
breadth like you know a thin line of sand that I can't
cast over. So even I'm very, very high, I didn't submerge the
earth because I can't sort of go beyond the shore. Okay, this
was before global warming. Okay. שנאמר shene'emar האותי לא תיראו נאם ה'
אם מפני לא תחילו אשר שמתי חול גבול לים, Ha'osi lo tiru
neum Hashem im panai lo tachilu asher samti chol gvul layam, have
you
will you not fear Me, I have made the sand the boundary
of the ocean, the ocean cannot pass beyond it. I mean obviously
in a high tide, low tide it gets a certain point on
that sand, but whatever, doesn't pass beyond. חק עולם ולא יעברנהו, chok
olam v'lo ya'avrenhu, an eternal edict that it will not pass it.
So again the way the רשב"ם... Rashbam... the מהרש"א Maharsha explains this,
I don't know how he deals with all the details, but he
basically it says it's like the nations of the earth, you know,
thinking that they can now, they're so powerful, they're you know sort
of like sort of like you know thinking that they're up into
the heavens, you know and so on and they're gonna do... are
they gonna come to
destroy... Okay.
אמר רבה Amar Rabbah לדידי חזי לי Lididi chazi li הורמין בר
לילית, Hormin bar Lilit,
הורמין בר לילית, Hormin bar Lilit, הורמין Hormin bar לילית, Lilit, I
saw this שד, shed, this demon הורמין Hormin the son of לילית,
Lilit, כי קא רהיט אקופא דשורא Ki ka rahit akupa deshura when
he was running on the top the of the
wall דמחוזא, Demachuza, the wall surrounding מחוזא Machuza which is where רבה
Rabbah lived, so, did he
live, did רבה Rabbah live in מחוזא? Machuza? No, they have it
switched to רבה בר בר חנה, Rabbah bar bar Chana,
maybe he lived in מחוזא Machuza also. Anyway, I saw this demon
running on the top of the wall of מחוזא, Machuza, ורהיט פרשא
כי רכיב חיותא מתותיה Verahit parsha ki rachiv chayuta mitutei and alongside
him was traveling,
was like galloping a horseman with, you know, with the horse running
under, you know, running underneath him, so a horseman riding a horse,
ולא יכיל ליה Velo yachil lei and couldn't catch up to him,
this demon was so fast he couldn't catch up to a fast-riding
horseman. זמנא חדא הוה מסרגני ליה תרתי כודנייתא, Zimna chada hava mesargnei
lei tarti kudenayta, one, there was one time that they saddled for
this demon two
mules, וקיימי אמתרי גישרי דרוגנג Vekaimei amtrei gishrei Derugnag and they, these
two mules were on two separate bridges of this river called רוגנג.
Rugnag. Anyway, ושבר מהאי להאי ומהאי להאי Veshavar mehai lehai umehai lehai
and the demon was sort of jumping from one mule to the
next and back and forth, so the mules were running on these
bridges and he was jumping over the huge body of water that
was between them and jumping from one mule to the next.
ונקיט תרי מזגי דחמרא בידיה Venakit trei mizgei dechamra bidei and he
had two cups of wine in his hands, ומוריק מהאי להאי ומהאי
להאי Umorik mehai lehai umehai lehai and as he was jumping, right,
he would like throw the wine out of one glass, jump to
the other mule and like catch the wine, you know, with the
other glass. And so you got the water, you got the wine
and the שד shed jumping from one mule to the next. ולא
נטפה מידי לערעא Velo natfa midi le'ara and one drop of wine
didn't hit the ground. ואותו היום יעלו שמים ירדו תהומות הוה, Ve'oto
hayom ya'alu shamayim yerdu tehomot hava, that was such a, it was
a super windy day and he was still able to do this.
It was a day where, you know, even, you know, those that
go down to the, because actually the beginning of this פסוק pasuk
is that speaks about those that go down to the ocean. So
it's again sort of echoing the whole, you know, sea-going and the
theme. So that it was, but it was so windy that they
would rise up to the heavens and go down to the depths,
הוה, hava, and he would nevertheless be able to do this amazing
feat. עד דשמעו בי מלכותא וקטלוהו Ad desham'u be malkuta vekatlohu until
this was heard in the king's castle and they killed him. Now,
which king was able to kill a שד? shed? So if you
look at the רשב"ם, Rashbam, his first explanation is the king of
the שדים. shedim. The king of the שדים shedim would not like
it that this שד shed was showing off his powers to the
humans. The other explanation he says was דאיכא דאמרי בי מלכא קיסר
De'ika de'amrei be malka Keisar Caesar, Caesar, שירא שלא יטול המלכות ממנו,
Sheyarei shelo yitol hamalchut mimenu, right, oh my God, there's such this
powerful demon out there, the Caesar had to protect his power. Of
course, how was he able to? But he says שהיה אותו שד
אדם הבא על השידה וידור בין הנשים. Shehaya oto shed adam haba
al hashidah vayador bein hanashim. Ah, so this was only a half-shed,
okay? It was, came through the copulation of a human being and
a female שדה shidah and therefore presumably I guess Caesar with his
army was able to conquer him. Yes.
רבה Rabbah lived in בבל. Bavel.
Yeah, without Caesar, there was no Caesar there. I understand. This is
the רשב"ם Rashbam speaking. Okay. All right. So anyway, yes, so you
tell, so you have something to say about this? Go for it.
Yes. Just a very simple,
just a bottom line. הורמין Hormin the son of לילית Lilit represents
the height of self-indulgence because of the שד shed and לילית Lilit
entices men towards...
Aha, so is that like sexual pleasure? And he's being self-indulgent like
showing off his power here?
The wall represents the תורה Torah of protection. Okay.
Some type of a way of translating this into some internal sort
of a conflict or how the powers of the different powers of
our יצר
הרע.
yeitzer
hara.
And then in the end הורמין'ס Hormin's activities for self-gratification are unproductive.
Aha, okay.
Got it. All right. Well, maybe it's hormones. There you go.
הורמין Hormin was hormones, הורמין. Hormin. What's the Hebrew word for hormones?
Is it something like הורמונים? hormonim? Right, הורמונים? hormonim? Right? הורמונים? hormonim?
Right,
that's from the animal's performance with sterile mules. Oh, yeah, yes. Self-indulgence.
Right, okay, there you go. It doesn't produce. Okay, got it. All
right. So אמר רבה Amar Rabbah לדידי חזי לי, Lididi chazi li,
I,
to me it was shown, אורזילא בר יומא Orzila bar yoma a
like antelope or whatever a ראם re'em is, they say it's a
ראם, re'em, so some type of a large beast, an antelope that
had just been born, a day-old antelope, דהוה כהר תבור, Dehava kehar
Tavor,
it was huge! I once saw now... or moving away from going
down into the sea, the seafarers and the other like sort of
magical or whatever mystical creatures. I saw this that was even just
one day old and it was the size of Mount Tabor. הר
תבור כמה הוי? Har Tavor kama havei? How much was that? ארבע
פרסי, Arba parsei, four פרסא. parsa. Once again a פרסא parsa is
four mil which is about four kilometers. ומשחא דצוארה תלתא פרסי, Umshacha
d'tzavara tlata parsei,
the length of its neck was three parsang. ובי מרבעתא דרישא, Uvei
marba'ata d'reisha, in the place where its head rests was פרסא ופלגא,
Parsa u'palga, a פרסא parsa and a half. רמא כופתא Rma kufta
and
it dropped a piece of dung, it relieved itself, וסכרה לירדנא Vsachra
l'Yardena
and that was so huge that it caused the Jordan River to
get stopped up. Okay, the Rashbam says until the rushing water finally
made its way through it again. So there was early pollution there,
they're already dumping sewage in that time. Do you have any interest
in comments, David, to say about that? Yeah, Charlie, let's see what
Charlie wants to say.
Well, I was going to say the tallest mountain in the world
is approximately a little more than two פרסא. parsa.
Okay, so four, okay, so there you go. David, anything? I can't
read it appropriate today at that stage. Yeah,
I probably should have read more of the Maharsha, my apologies, not,
I want to leave it open for you to come up with
your own interpretations of this. Okay, ואמר רבה בר בר חנה, V'amar
Rabbah bar bar Chana, Rabbah bar bar Chana said, לדידי חזי לי
ההיא
אקרוקשתא. Lididi chazi li hahi akrukashta. So you know what an אקרוקשתא
akrukashta is? Rashbam says it is a צפרדע, Tzfardei'a, a croaker. A
croak, I assume that's the same thing, to croak, אקרוקשתא. Akrukashta. Okay,
so a frog, דהויא כי אקרא דהגרוניא, D'havya ki akra d'Hagronya, that
it was the size of the city, אקרא דהגרוניא. Akra d'Hagronya. ואקרא
דהגרוניא כמה הויא, V'akra d'Hagronya kama havya, and how big is that
city? שיתין בתי, Shitin batei, or town, sixty houses. Okay, so a
frog the size of sixty houses. אתא תנינא, Ata tanina, came a
snake, ובלעה U'valah and swallowed it. אתא פושקנצא, Ata pushkantza,
funny word, came, I'm going to say perfect timing for פסח, Pesach,
חד גדיא. Chad Gadya. Okay, then came a raven ובלעה לתנינא U'valah
l'tanina and swallowed the snake. This is a little bit of a
חד גדיא, Chad Gadya, this is very interesting.
Along came a snake, swallowed the frog, along came a raven, swallowed
the snake.
What? ובלעה לתנינא? U'valah l'tanina?
Yeah, well תנין Tanin can be like a what? Crocodile. Crocodile. Oh
that's interesting. The Rashbam I think says, why did I think it
was a snake?
He says, yeah just
no he doesn't say.
He says a sea monster.
Oh okay. What? תנין, Tanin, modern Hebrew it's like a crocodile,
תנינים הגדולים, Taninim hagedolim, right, that's true.
It's like a lizard,
I thought sometimes it means like a serpent or a snake
but it's related to the crocodile.
Right, right, right, right, right.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. I think it's got a range of meanings. Okay,
sea monster, crocodile, then came a raven and swallowed that, ובלעה לתנינא,
U'valah l'tanina, וסליק יתיב באילנא, Vsillik yatib b'ilana,
and then the raven went and rested on a branch, a tree
branch. תא חזי כמה נפיש חילא דאילנא, Ta chazi kama nafish cheila
d'ilana, imagine how powerful the tree had to be that one branch
could support the raven that ate the sea monster that ate the
frog that was the size of
sixty houses. Okay,
I do not have any idea what the point of all this
is.
Okay. Maharsha's got a whole thing about this, that the תלמידי חכמים
Talmidei Chachamim are compared to the frogs and goes to the birds.
Okay, alright.
All of them are one after the other. What? It sounds like
the bad guys each,
oh like it's a dog-eat, like they're consuming one another, right, so
like dog-eat-dog type of a world sort of thing.
Like the Greeks that conquered.
Oh I see, I see, uh-huh. And then what's the tree that's
supporting them all? The תורה? Torah?
God?
That's why frogs do.
Yeah, I guess, maybe because they talk a lot, because they croak,
what?
He says here the tree represents the תורה Torah supporter as it
is written, it is a tree of life for those
who, right, that's why I imagined the תורה Torah association.
Uh-huh, okay. Okay, ואמר רבה, V'amar Rabbah, so maybe like those that
are strengthened by the תורה Torah are stronger than all of the
you know, that could be the idea, right, learning תורה Torah supports
the world so all of these nations think they're powerful, so that's
a nice interpretation.
Okay, good. We'll write our own commentary on this I guess. ואמר
רבה בר בר חנה, V'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana, אי לאו דהוינא
התם, Ei lav d'havina hatam, had I not been there and seen
this לא הימני, Lo heimani, I would not have believed it. So
I was sort of wondering if there was like a little bit
like of a maybe this is obviously myself reading into a little
ironic thing so like I'm thinking I'm reading things like okay but
I wasn't there so maybe I shouldn't believe it. Anyway, so alright,
but anyway, ואמר רבה בר בר חנה, V'amar Rabbah bar bar Chana,
זימנא חדא הוה קא אזלינן בספינתא. Zimna chada hava ka azlinan b'sefinta.
once I was going on a boat, so now he himself was
going on a boat. וחזינן ההוא כוורא v'chazinan ha-hu kavra and I
saw a fish, for a sea creature, choosing it's a fish since
he's using the כוורא. kavra. ויתבא ליה אכלתינא באוסיה v'yatba leh achlatina
b'usya
that a sort of a mound of dirt or mud was sort
of settled on its back. Wait one minute, is that right? No,
no, no, I'm sorry, I misread it, I'm jumping ahead to the
next story. ויתבא ליה אכלתינא. v'yatba leh achlatina. אכלתינא achlatina is the
name of some type of a parasite, some type of a bug
went ahead and settled itself באוסיה b'usya in its nostrils. ואדחוהו מיא
v'adchuhu maya and so he and then it died. It died as
a result of this parasite. So you have a dead fish. So
the dead fish was sort of cast ashore by the water. So
it was cast ashore by the water. ושדיוהו לגודא u'shadyuhu l'guda it
was cast to the bank. וחרוב מיניה שיתין מחוזי v'charuv mineh shitin
machozei
and this fish was so huge that when it was cast to
the bank it like landed on like 60 cities and destroyed 60
cities. Okay. ואכלו מיניה שיתין מחוזי v'achalu mineh shitin machozei
and because it was so huge then those cities then you know
the neighboring towns were able to go ahead and have like a
lot of they were able to feast for a long time, so
it provided food for 60 ostensibly other cities, other towns. ומלחו מיניה
שיתין מחוזי. u'malchu mineh shitin machozei. Now that was while it was
fresh, but you know you weren't going to get a chance to
eat it all. So then they had to preserve it. So they
salted it to שיתין מחוזי shitin machozei another 60 towns were able
to preserve it for future eating. ומלו מחד גלגלא דעיניה תלת מאה
גרבי משחא u'malu mi-chad galgala d'eineh tlat me'ah garbei mishcha from one
of its eyes they were able to fill
300 like you know barrels of oil. They used fish eye, provided
fish oil. Okay. וכי הדרן לבתר תריסר ירחי שתא v'chi hadran l'vatar
treisar yarchei shata and when I returned to that place after 12
months, חזינן דהוו מנסרי מגרמי מטללתא chazinan d'havu mnasrei migarmei mtalalta
they were cutting from its bones beams, odds like מטללתא mtalalta is
the word for a סוכה, sukkah, rafters out of the fish bones
because ostensibly by that time they had eaten all of the fish,
all of the flesh of the fish and now they were cutting
out you know beams out of its bones. ויתבי למבנינהו הנך מחוזי
v'yatvi l'mivneinhu hanach machozei and they were going to use them to
rebuild the 60 cities that had been destroyed.
This fish would have been big enough to swallow Jonah.
More than that if it's big enough to destroy 60 cities. All
right, I have no idea what to make of this.
I thought you said something
about the צדיקים tzadikim eating this. Oh yeah, about the לויתן levyatan
being eaten by the צדיקים לעתיד לבוא, tzadikim l'atid lavo, so maybe
there's some sense about that. What do you got there in the
bottom? It's huge. Okay,
one sentence. What does the fish represent?
All right, we got the ship. All right, now let's take a
look. Let's go down.
Homily of the sixth story. What ship?
The death of the fish in אשור Ashur represents the death of
a person. God is particular with righteous people. They sometimes die on
account of a small misdeed. Oh, that's the little bug that got
into the thing. A sin contaminates a person, therefore compared to a
creeping thing, etc. How do people react to the death of a
righteous person? Three classes. The first class reacts with extreme abstinence. They
see etc., etc. I don't know. So that's the second class the
opposite way, they perceive it as ultimate end of all activity.
All right, so anyway, so the different towns are how they're reacting
to the death of the fish and the death of a righteous
person.
All right, you can go ahead and figure that one out. All
right,
so where are we? I said next time I will try to
have done more of the מהרש"א Maharsha to give you some type
of an interpretation, but you know maybe it's fun for you to
try to come up with your own. So now it says like
this. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה, va-amar Rabbah bar bar Chana, Rabbah
bar Bar Chana says, זימנא חדא הוה קאזלינן בספינתא, zimna chada hava
ka-azlinan b'sefinata, once I was going on a boat. זימנא חדא הוה
קאזלינן בספינתא, zimna chada hava ka-azlinan b'sefinata, once I was going on
a boat. וחזינן ההוא כוורא v'chazinan ha-hu kavra and I saw a
fish, דיתבא ליה חלא אגביה. d'yatba leh chala agabeih. That's what I
was jumping ahead to. And sand had settled on the back of
this fish. I mean I guess you imagine it as like a
huge whale or something. וקדח אגמא עילויה v'kadach agma ilaveih
and like and grass was growing, reeds were growing from the sand.
סברינן יבשתא היא, savrinan yaveshta hi, we thought it was like this
little island in the middle of the ocean. We just saw the
sand and the grass. וסלקינן, v'salkinan, we went up to the island,
we settled our boat on it. ואפינן ובשלינן אגביה v'afinan u'vashlinan agabeih
and we baked and we cooked, you know we had a little
picnic, we settled, we got ourselves you know we camped out there.
וכד חם גביה, u'chad cham gabeih, now when the back of the
fish got hot because we were making a fire on this island,
איתהפיך, ithapich, it turned over. ואי לאו דהוה מקרבא ספינתא, v'i lav
d'hava mkarva sefinata,
and if our boat had not been nearby, הוה טבעינן, hava tav'inan,
we would have drowned. All right, so I don't know what this
is. I mean I imagine you can view this as the whole
metaphor of the soul goes down to the world and you know
and it thinks that it's like permanent and then you settle yourself
in and then you know you don't realize that you're going to...
Whatever, you know, you'll- it could turn over, you'll die, you have
to prepare yourself for the next world, something along those lines. You
can אידך פירושא זיל גמרא. Idach Peirusha Zil Gemara. Okay. ואמר רבה
בר בר חנה. Va'amar Rabbah Bar Bar Channah. Rabbah Bar Bar Channah
said: Yes, this story wants to get associated with the wicked. Initially
they're
friendly.
Ah,
the fish is the wicked, right?
So then you're in the hands and
then they turn over and they betray you. I see. Okay.
So the ship and the fish is reference
to the help from below. Got it. So in the first case,
the fish was a righteous person who died and in this case,
the fish is the wicked people. Got it. Okay. ואמר רבה בר
בר חנה. Va'amar Rabbah Bar Bar Channah. Rabbah Bar Bar Channah said:
זימנא חדא, Zimna Chada, one time, הוי אזילנא בספינתא, Havi Azilna Besafinta,
I was going in a boat, וסגי ספינתא בין שיצא לשיצא, Vesagai
Safinta Bein Shitsa Leshitsa, and the boat was swimming between one fin
and the next fin of the fish. Now it seems like what
we're talking about is something at the top and at the bottom
of the fish. So
דכיוורא דרבה Dekivra Derabbah of the fish, תלתא יומי ותלתא לילוותא, Tlata
Yomi Vetlata Leilvata,
three days and three nights. Apparently the way it's sort of seems
to be imagining it. Now you get to see me draw a
fish, which is like not so great. Okay, here, that's my fish.
Anyway, so here's what and here's the thing in the back. So
the boat is going-
here's your boat. Okay. Your boat is going this way. The fish
is going that way. All right. So basically that means that it
should take less time for it to cover the length of the
fish because they're both you know they're both going in opposite directions.
So we were going from one- it was taking us three days
and three nights to try to travel from one fin to the
next. איהו בזיקיפא ואנן בשיפולה. Ihu Bezikeifa Veanan Beshipula.
It was going like against the wind and we were going with
the wind at our back. So that also means that we had
the extra added sort of assistance of the wind. And it still
took us three days and three nights to cover the length of
the fish. וכי תימא לא מסגיא ספינתא טובא, Vechi Teima Lo Masgya
Safinta Tuva, now you'll think, eh, maybe the boat didn't go so
fast. That's not a big deal. You know, it was a slow
boat. No. דכי אתא רב דימי אמר, Dechi Ata Rav Dimi Amar,
when Rav Dimi came he said: כמיחם קומקומא דמיא, Kemeicham Kumkuma Demaya,
when the time it takes to heat up a little kettle of
water in a few minutes, מסגיא שיתין פרסי, Masgya Shitin Parsei, that
boat was so fast it could go sixty parasangs. So it was
a super fast boat and it was going with the wind and
the fish was going the opposite direction and it still took three
days and three nights to cover the length of the fish. Okay.
ושדי פרשא גירא, Veshadi Parasha Geira, and oh, and if you were
to-
and if
somebody were to- a horseman were to shoot an arrow, דקדמה ליה,
Dekadma Lei, this fish would sort of, you know, would beat out
the arrow. That's how fast this fish would go. What do you
got there for us David?
This is just to hint- it's helpful to intensity- the other nations
of the world, okay, that- they are not exiled, they live in
their
homelands like fish in water. Aha. The ship and the fish is
the Jewish nation. Ah,
I see.
So
we're- we're always in exile. They're always moving against the wind because
the nations move against the will of Hashem. Uh-huh. The Jews who
abide by the Torah travel with the wind. And three days is
the time it takes for fasting and repentance. Okay.
All right. Got it, got it. You're above the water, not there
inside. Okay. I thought עוסק בתורה Osek BaTorah was like the fish
in the water, wasn't it? Okay. ואמר רב אשי, Va'amar Rav Ashi,
and then said Rav
Ashi: ההיא גילדנא דימא הוי. Hahi Gildana De'yama Havai. This-
that fish was this- the name of the fish was- was a
גילדנא. Gildana. That was just the type of fish it was. דאית
ליה תרתי שייצי, De'it Lei Tartei Shaitsei, that had these two fins.
So just to know what fish we're talking about. Okay. ואמר רבה
בר בר חנה. Va'amar Rabbah Bar Bar Channah. Rabbah Bar Bar Channah
said: זימנא חדא הוי אזילנא בספינתא, Zimna Chada Havai Azilna Besafinta, once
I was going in a boat, וחזינא ההיא ציפרא, Vechazina Hahi Tsipra,
I saw a bird, דקאים עד קרסוליה במיא, Dekayim Ad Karsulei Bemaya,
it was up to its ankles or קרסול Karsul is an ankle-
up to its ankles in water, ורישיה ברקיע, Verishei Berakia,
and its head was way up in the sky. ואמינא ליכא מיא.
Ve'amina Leika Maya. Now we thought that, oh, it's like it's only
up to its ankles in water, so there must be that there's
not so much water there. Of course you would think if you
see the fish with its head in the sky- that bird, excuse
me- that it might be that even for its ankles that's a
lot of water underneath. But we figured eh, it's just the ankles,
can't be too much water here. Okay. ובעינן למיחת לאקורי נפשין, Uva'inan
Lemichat Le'akorei Nafshin, and we figured hey, let's go- let's go swimming,
let's go into the water, cool off ourselves. ונפק בת קלא ואמר
לן, Venafak Bat Kala Ve'amar Lan, and a heavenly voice came out
and said to us: לא תיחתו הכא, Lo Teichatu Hacha, don't- don't
go down- don't go down into the water here. It's very, very
deep. דנפלה ליה חציצא לבר נגרא, Denafla Lei Chatsitsa Levar Nagra, an
axe of a carpenter once fell into this water, הא שבע שנין,
Ha Sheva Shanim, for seven years. ולא קמטיא ארעא vlo kamatya ara
and still has yet to hit the bottom of the water. So
it's pretty darn deep. ולאו משום דנפישי מיא, vlo mishum dnefishi maya,
it's not really because the water is so deep, אלא משום דרדיפי
מיא, ela mishum dradifi maya, the current is so strong that that
prevented it from falling to the bottom. Okay, there's the... you got
anything for us? Yes, it teaches that students shouldn't go into esoteric
disciplines. Oh, esoteric... too deep for them. It looks easy for the
masters of the קבלה, Kabbalah, but a שטיפתא shitafta has across the
רישא, reisha, the bird represents the Jewish people whose
feet are firmly planted in reality and yet their heads reach the
heavens. Ah, like סולם Sulam of יעקב, Yakov, yes. And sometimes they
believe that they can enjoy the worlds of life like other nations,
at which point they are warned that what appears to them as
שלווה shalva is in fact turbulent waves fraught with dangers. Aha, that's
what I saw, I mean I didn't see that in particular, but
I thought that the metaphor of like oh, it doesn't look like
it'll be, looks like it'll be nice and it's very dangerous, I
don't you know indulge, so he's treating it like indulge in the
sort of physical pleasures or you know the indulgences of the other
nations. Okay, interesting. All right, moving on. I wonder what the seven
years was about the axe going down. The waters are anyway. So,
where are we? אמר רב אשי. Amar Rav Ashi. So said Rav
Ashi. ההוא זיז שדי הוא. Hahu Ziz Shadai hu. Ah, the name
of that bird was זיז שדי, Ziz Shadai, so this may be
a reason to associate with the Jewish people because right, it's like
the God is שדי, Shadai, דכתיב dechtiv וזיז שדי עמדי. veZiz Shadai
imadi. Okay, is with me, is with God, you know, so it's
and it's just God's name there. So it's שדי Shadai or שדי?
Shadai? Oh, was it שדי? Sadai? They have it as שדי. Sadai.
Oh,, my mistake then. Okay, my mistake, so if it's not God's
name. Okay, ואמר רבה בר בר חנה, v'amar Rabbah Bar Bar Channah,
זימנא חדא הוה קאזילנא במדברא, zimna chada hava ka azilna b'midbara, we
were once going in the wilderness, וחזינא הני אווזי, v'chazina hanei avazi,
and we saw these geese, דשמטי גדפייהו משמנייהו, dishamti gadpaihu mishamnaihu, and
their feathers would fall off of them, they were so fat that
their feathers would fall off because of their fatness. You know, if
anywhere you expect to find fat geese, I don't think it would
be the wilderness, but okay. Fattening thing with feathers. You know, I
need some suspension of disbelief. Exactly. Okay, וקנגדי נחלי דמשחא מתותייהו, v'kangadi
nachalei d'mishcha mitutaiahu, and a river of fat would you know was
flowing under them because they were so fat I guess and their
body pressed against the ground maybe it caused the fat to dissolve.
A river of fat was flowing under them. אמינא להו amina lehu
and I said to these geese, אית לן לגוייכו חלקא לעלמא דאתי,
it lan l'gavaichu chelka l'alma d'ati, in the world to come will
we be able to benefit from you? Will we be able to
eat you? You look so delicious. So חדא דלי גדפא chada dali
gadpa one lifted up its wing to show me apparently yes you'll
be able to eat from my nice fat belly, וחדא דלי אטמא,
v'chada dali atma, and one lifted up its leg, I guess, you
know, you'll be able to eat a nice פולקע pulke or something.
So go figure what that means. כי אתא לקמיה דרבי אלעזר, Ki
ata l'kamei d'Rabbi Elazar, when I came to Rabbi Elazar, אמר לי,
amar li, he said to me, עתידין ישראל ליתן עליהם את הדין.
atidin Yisrael liten aleihem et hadin. In the end the Jewish people
will have to you know make an accounting for them, pay for
them. Now what do you mean? What does that even mean? So
the רשב"ם Rashbam says two lines from the bottom, שבחטאתם מתעכב משיח,
shebechatatam mitakev mashiach, for your sin, you know, you would be able
to be already benefiting from these delicious geese but the reason, but
it's taking so long because of your sin. Now what does that
mean that we'll be punished, what are we being punished? So look
at this: שיש להם צער בעלי חיים לאותם אווזים מחמת שומנן. sheyesh
lahem tzaar baalei chayim l'otam avazim machmat shumnan. Here they are, these
fat geese that were created for the Messianic times, but because the
Messiah is being delayed, then they have to go around and it's
so painful for them being so fat and you're going to have
to pay for it. Which obviously is like so interesting because you
think about like veal and foie gras which is about fattening, it's
fattening geese right? It's goose liver. Right. Force-feeding them. So here you're
going to pay for the suffering of these animals. So you know,
there you go. Okay. ואמר רבה בר בר חנה, v'amar Rabbah Bar
Bar Channah, זימנא חדא הוה קאזילנא במדברא, zimna chada hava ka azilna
b'midbara, I was once going in the wilderness, ואתלווי בהדן ההוא טייעא,
v'itlavai behadan hahu taya, a certain Arab wanderer, not wanderer, itinerant? Yeah,
itinerant. Bedouin, yeah exactly, was going with us.
דהוה שקיל עפרא d'hava shakil afra and
he was able to take some the sand, ומורח ליה v'morach leh
and smell it, ואמר הא אורחא לדוכתא פלן והא אורחא לדוכתא פלן.
v'amar ha orcha l'duchta palan v'ha orcha l'duchta palan. This is the
way to go to here, this is the way to go to
here. He could sort of know, you know, where things were based
on smelling the sand. ואמינא ליה v'amina leh and we said to
him, כמה מרחיקן ממיא, kama marchikan mimaya, how far is it from
water? אמר לן amlan הב לי עפרא, hav li afra, give me
some sand that I can smell it. יהבינא ליה, yavina lei, we
gave it. אמר לן amlan תמני פרסי, tamni parsei, eight parses. תנינן
ויהבינא ליה, taninan v'yavina lei, then we gave him some other sand
again, and אמר לן, amlan, he said to it's דמחרחנא d'marchatan תלתא
פרסי. tlasa parsei. So it's now three parses away. אפיכתא ליה, afichta
lei, we reversed it for him, ולא יכילינא ליה, v'lo yachilna lei,
and we couldn't best him. That's not exactly clear what it means,
but basically they were trying to give him sand that they had
taken from some other place to test and see, was he just
making it up or was he really smelling the sand? And anyway,
whatever test they tried to do with him, like it was clear,
you know, that he was, he passed. We couldn't prove him to
be wrong, you know. So anyway, I mean, there actually are, I
mean, you know, people, right, yeah, trackers, and they, you know, can
really, I don't know how they do it or what exactly they
do, but it looks like something like this. Okay, we will end
here. The next one is, gets to yet a whole another discussion.
So next time maybe I'll have a chance to see a little
bit more מהרש"א, Maharsha, but enjoy writing your own פירוש peirush on
these next few גמרות. Gemaras.